<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2474 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2474.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2475 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2475.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3260 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3260.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl'
             href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<!-- Change the title here -->

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-york-dart-dscp-rtp-00" ipr="trust200902">
  
  <front>

    <title abbrev="Limitations of Using DiffServ And DSCP With RTP">Limitations of Using 
    Differentiated Services (DiffServ) With Real-time Communications Protocols</title>


    <author fullname="Dan York" initials="D." surname="York">
      <organization>Internet Society</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Keene</city>
          <region>N.H.</region>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1-802-735-1624</phone>
        <email>dyork@lodestar2.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="David Black" initials="D." surname="Black">
      <organization>EMC</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>176 South Street</street>
          <city>Hopkinton</city>
          <region>MA</region>
          <code>01748</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 508 293-7953</phone>
        <email>david.black@emc.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Cullen Jennings" initials="C." surname="Jennings">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>
          <street>MS: SJC-21/2</street>
          <city>San Jose</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95134</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 408 421-9990</phone>
        <email>fluffy@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    
    <date year="2014" />

    <area>RAI</area>

    <workgroup>DiffServ Applied to Real-time Transports</workgroup>

    <keyword>DiffServ,DSCP,RAI</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document explains the interaction between DiffServ, DiffServ Code Points
      (DSCP) and real-time communication protocols such as the Real-time Transport Protocol 
      (RTP).  This document explains the limitations that exist with DiffServ and DSCP
      when used with RTP in general as well as in specific RTCTWEB cases.</t>
      
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
    
      <!-- Initial intro text taken from the DART charter.  Needs to be improved. -->
          
      <t>Differentiated Services (DiffServ) and DiffServ code points (DSCP) can be used
in some situations to provide quality of service (QoS). Packets with different
markings can be reordered, which can cause poor interaction with a transport
protocol that is responsive to reordering. When RTP streams or other real-time
media (sub-)flows are used with different DSCP values with the same transport
5-tuple, there may be transport protocol interactions. There are also
environments where the DSCP markings are removed or remarked.</t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

 
    <section anchor="DiffServ" title="Background on Usage of DiffServ">   
      <!-- This text taken from James Polk's email to DISPATCH to serve as a base -->
       
      <t>Various transport protocols exist today for various reasons; mostly because there 
      was a need for a behavior that the IP layer just could not provide, or a behavior 
      that another transport protocol didn't have (at the time, in some cases). For 
      example, both a type of congestion control and an ability to reorder at the 
      receiver out of order packets necessitated the need for the development of a 
      transport layer to handle both capabilities better. The result was TCP. There are 
      now multiple transport protocols (i.e., TCP, UDP, SCTP, etc.) that have various 
      behaviors. These behaviors are not the same depending on the network circumstance 
      a/each packet finds itself in as it traverses through the network.</t>

      <t>With the IP layer, and not part of the 5-tuple identifier, DiffServ code points 
      (DSCP) can be used in situations to provide quality of service (QoS), but in fact 
      it is a class of service (COS) differentiation they provide. These 64 different 
      values are found within the old TOS byte. There is nothing in the DSCP field but 
      zeros most of the time (i.e., Best Effort). As specified within RFC 2474 and 2475 
      is called a per hop behavior (PHB). Hence most packets receive a best effort PHB. 
      An important aspect of a PHB is that it is just that, and a packet, and indirectly 
      its user, needs to be prepared to have its DSCP remarked to another value one or 
      more times, or any time it traverses a layer node.</t>

      <t>With the desire to now explore other than best effort DSCP markings of RTP 
      streams or other real-time media (sub-)flows, certain realities, say for example 
      reordering of packets within a stream or flow, not all transport protocols behave 
      the same. Some will have their DSCP of a non-zero value set to zero by some router 
      before the destination, or another non-zero value that is different from the packet 
      that it was originally set to.</t>
    </section>  
    
    <section anchor="RTP" title="Background on Usage of RTP">
      <t>(This section will provide explain about the needs of RTP.</t>

    </section>
    <section anchor="RTCWEB" title="RTCWEB Examples">
      <t>(This section will provide examples of DiffServ/DSCP limitations with
      regard to RTCWEB.)</t>

    </section>   
    
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This document is the result of many conversations that have occurred within
      multiple RAI and TRANSPORT area working groups.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document includes no request to IANA.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>(Need to understand if there are any security considerations to include.)</t>
      
    </section>
  </middle>

 
  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">

      &RFC2119;

      
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

      <!-- Need pointers to DiffServ-related RFCs and drafts. Three are listed here as 
      examples, but the proper list should be identified. -->
       
       &RFC2474;
       &RFC2475;       
       &RFC3260; 
       
      <!-- Pointers to appropriate RTCWEB documents? -->
      
    </references>

  
  </back>
</rfc>